Today's speaker is Xavier Marshall who's a Coke terminal student
in the perception in action lab.
and this is a
project that is based on.
His master. Well, his master's project this title the
new tool for visualization of gays data in 3D
virtual environments the unity playbacks
system Suite Suites. Yes.
Branding is fun.
All right, that includes my presentation.
So yeah, as Brett said this will
working on so to maybe add some clarity to
what is a kind of messy title. Essentially when
I'm working on here is a plug-in for Unity that will allow
experimenters to create sort of
frame by frame playbacks of their virtual environments. So
the behavior that you end up getting is going to end up very similar to
a video player and we'll explore that later. But first let's kind
of get into the background a little bit.
So I want to talk generally about the landscape of virtual
reality eye tracking and simulated
environments in general right sort of
to create a lead-up to why we've made this so speaking
generally game engines have become a really
ubiquitous and really accessible tool for
creating experiments rapidly, especially within
the field of human behavior.
So alongside that we've also had really great
increases in the portability of virtual reality
the accuracy and reliability of eye trackers and
the ability to kind of combine all of these different experimental paradigms
together, which has been really really great but
also comes with a few problems as these experiments become
more common.
So first starters, this is just inherent to gaze data
in general. It is noisy. It is difficult to interpret and it's
even worse when you're dealing with naturalistic studies
that have complex environments
lots of visual clutter things of that
nature that really complicate your scene and make it difficult to
Intuit. What's happening based off
of just a sort of a glance at the data.
Which is why we want to sort of add more potent
visualizations to it.
Alongside that we have just this broader open source
landscape that kind of surrounds Unity, which is honestly really really
great in robust, but lacking in one core way and
that's the ability that it has to sort of Aid researchers
and their data analysis. There are
plenty of tools that are really great for like data collection experiment formatting
assets that make replicating
certain experimental to paradigms very easy, but data analysis
is incredibly under explored within the open source Unity community and
that's where I'd like to sort of settle in a little bit and bolster.
And so again, let's get back
to the unity playback Suites a system
many different names. I'll probably
call it the playback Suite from here on but again, it's that
open source toolkit that gets you frame by frame replays of
your experimental trials, right? And
so in order to do this, we create essentially a carbon copy
of replica of your experimental environments and within
that you can start, you know, constructing your
own custom 3D visualizations, you can
export additional data import data that was not
originally recorded while in unity as well
as a few other things. And so we want to try to make this
a very kind of extensible engineeric tool that can be provided that
can be utilized in any kind of research so
long as it's kind of fundamentally compatible
with the playback Suite similarly. We
kind of want this to really focus on leveraging the
the robust power that Unity has to offer as
a 3D game engine which are incredible at rendering
graphics and processing that information with Incredible
ease the apis that are
included honestly take care of so much work that if you're maybe
in the field computer vision would have to kind of reconstruct from the ground
up if you only had video
Go ahead.
Yeah, so we
that that's one part of it. So we
try to go beyond simply overlays. You'll kind
of see as we go forward as I talk more about sort of the the features that expand
beyond that, but what's really interesting about
this is that you can because you can bring your data back into a reconstructed scene.
You have multiple different camera perspectives that render
your data from from different angles that visualize
it in different ways. And so you can yeah just
do those simple overlays and you'll see some but then you're also going
to see kind of a little bit beyond that so we
will get into that. Hope you're excited.
So for now I just want to do a quick overview of the the content.
We're going to cover throughout this presentation. So first
things first, I want to review some very basic terminology and
principles within Unity so that we
all have a good kind of Baseline understanding of what we describing here.
Then I'm going to go into the unity
playback Suites. It's features. It's sort of design mentality
how we landed where we are today?
And then I'm going to kind of walk through how to integrate
upbs into a very simple sort of
mock simulation. So that way you kind of know the basics of
all the steps in order to get integrated and kind of understand how this tool
works. Then we're going to dive a little bit into to case
study experiments that will kind of
go more in depth about the applications of these features as
well as gesture toward the next steps for the development
of the software seeing as it's only February.
so to start
you need primer we have scenes. So
a scene in unity is simply your blank
canvas. It is a 3D environment that contains all of
your game objects and So within the scene
Are the game objects now these represent characters their
props? They can be scenery. They
can also be environmental State information. There's
all kinds of data that can be stored Within game
objects. And so you'll kind of see here this
image on left hand side of a panel that you need
generates sort of depicting all your game objects when this within the scene
as well as in the right hand side that same scene. I showed
in that early image now populated with game objects. One
thing you'll know is that there are more objects detail
on the left hand side. This is because Unity has a lot more data on
the back end but the playback Suite is only concerned with
the visual stimulus. That's the stuff. We want to try to replicate when we
create our copy of your scene.
Moving on from there. We have components which are just modular pieces
of behavior sort of exposed to Unity. You can
you can apply these behaviors onto different
game objects and multitude or different configurations
and those behaviors are defined by
scripts which are just a little chunks of c-sharp code or very
large chunks depending on how you're feeling that
day.
So
with that out of the way, we're going to talk a little bit about the design principles and
the playback Suite so really want
to emphasize again like this being open source drive
so much of the trajectory of this project every design
decision every every feature
that we add every
every line of code that gets written a sort of filtered through
this lens of needing to be perfectly as workable as
possible to somebody who's unfamiliar with the code and as
simple and straightforward as it
can be we really want this to be kind of maximally accessible to non-programmers
or very inexperienced Unity programmers
the kind of thing that you can hand to an undergraduate maybe in their
first or second semester and within weeks they can probably pick
it up. That's what we're looking to go for here.
We know that analysis can take a wide wide
variety of different forms across different experiments and there's
no way to like properly standardize like what analyzes
you want to find we can't standardize this framework and
we can make it as extensible as possible. So that way
any analyzes that you're interested in adding will be
presents.
and finally
Onto the more onto the topic of standardization. We
have a tool called the unity experiment
framework that I want to describe and go a little bit into because the
way this tool works is actually pivotal to the operation
of the playback speeds and this where it
gets maybe a little bit complicated. So feel free to slow me
down if need be
All right. So the unity experiment framework handles
the entirety of the data
collection for simulation compatible with
the playback Suite. So what it
does is it basically standardizes your data formatting ensures consistent
data recording it's widely
used. It's open source and genuinely, I would
consider it sort of a non-brainer to use in unity
simulations because it's so potent
and and so
it works so well to record your data. It's kind
of handle that boilerplate stuff that you have
to do a cross experiments and I want to go a little bit more into the unity
experiment framework and how that works that will
lead sort of into the setup for the playback Suites. All right.
So the unique experiment framework collects stimulus
and experiment State data using something called trackers.
These are components that you define via scripts
and you attach the game objects. Once they are
attach the game object. You'll get all kinds of data recorded based on
what you define, right? That's sort
of the the main squeeze of UXF. That's what
you want to be up. That's where we're going to be working with most directly and those
trackers are going to play a key role in how we
replicate your environments.
UXF also offers us the ability to organize their
experiments in a very standardized way and it
really is great for like allowing us to track the the
data we collect on participants. So you kind
of see by this diagram it can divide your experiment based off
some configuration into different sessions for every participants
upon which you can split it up up more
into blocks, which are just really chunks of
meaningfully different trials for your experiments all
this is globally available State information
and again,
Useful for the playback Suite go ahead.
Yes.
yeah, so actually
Yeah, I'll probably go into that. But I can use this one right here to explain
that more clearly. So for example,
I have this this tracker here which is
just for kind of maintaining the the camera. Now this doesn't
show much of the scripting but you can kind of see has a
few parameters here for different pieces of data including the
headers that go into your file a descriptor the name
of the file and then I think as I move forward I'm
going to kind of go into the way the code is sort of operating to
get data into that tracker.
Massage you had a question maybe MIT open
source.
Yes.
So yeah, there are a few challenges to getting something like
the playback Suite up and running.
Um, so kind of as you
might understand simple data
collection processes don't contain a complete environmental record if
I have a cube and I'm recording the position and
rotation of that cube, right that's information. I'd want to track through a
Tracker the 3D position and the rotation that tells
me nothing about the color of the cube the bounding boxes
around the cube the scale of the cube all this
additional kind of 3D information that could be relevant but
isn't sort of immediately available
with the data we typically record and so by creating a
copy of your scene. We're sort
of using unity's abilities to bake in
all of that 3D information innately.
Which allows us sort of get around that incomplete record.
Right. We also know that adding like adding
new features like this to a scene that's
already existing would be massively would be massive in terms
of overhead. You know, you'd have to you know, toggle off
certain code that runs for your trials. We don't want to mess with any of that.
We want to have the sort of playback version of
your scene completely separate. We also need
to accommodate for like stimulus that's recorded different rates and things of that nature. There
are a lot of kind of nitty-gritty details that can
really bug things down. But I want to get into an example that hopefully
add a lot of clarity I think to sort
of the concepts we've been throwing around so far
And so here's we're going to kind of go over through the priests through the
procedure of how to create a very simple playback environment. And
so what I've got running the resolution will
eventually catch up what I've got running is a,
you know, very simple like a mock experiments.
It's going to contain some 3D Primitives just moving around
on their own and the scene there's a
resolution so you're gonna see very simple movements now in
the background you kind of saw that little panel that little
UI interface that was
for kind of initializing UXF. So in the background you XF
is collecting data on the position and the rotation as
well as the scale for this guy of all these game objects. It's
even recording information on your camera. And so
now UXF is doing all that writing this information
to a file and
that sort of what I want to demonstrate here, right? So what do we
do with that information UXF has done a great job written
the information for us.
How does this how does all this work, right so?
We take step back.
each stimulus
Has a Tracker right that tracker being
that chunk of c-sharp code. You can kind of see that box in the middle there. This
is illustrating the position and rotation. So what the
tracker is doing essentially is it's saying I want to record
the X Y and Z position plus the X
Y and Z, uh Euler rotation for every
single game object from there.
The track is going to Output a CSV file, you know,
indicating all the data we've collected.
And this is where the playback speed comes in.
Users of the playback Suite will additionally need to create what
I call Reflections. So reflection sort of
does the opposite of a Tracker so it takes
the data file produced by a Tracker and it's
it tells Unity how to
recreate those same pieces of information it recorded
So if a Tracker is recording the if a
Tracker is made by writing the XYZ position
to a file a reflection is made by telling
unity set the xyp position of
a game object Sasha.
and
So simple things what is
the data format that the track is started. So how
does the CC file look like then you mentioned
that there's a copy of the scene now. We see it entails many environmental
variables, right? Then you mentioned that a a
unique experimental
framework attracted attached a single subject and
it records the subject.
Physician rotation and scale now this if
it's an object is being
tracked and it doesn't track the entire seamlessly right as they
could be many other environmental variables. So what exactly is
being tracked what variables are being
tracked and how what is the what is the
format? They're being stored? Yeah, so that's actually it's
a great question. Let me actually back up a little bit to this video and I'll
sort of illustrate that so for every
single one of these objects each one has a Tracker attached recording the
position and the rotation. Those are
the only two meaningful chunks of data and it's going to be recording that data for
every single frame of the experiment.
And so this is a bit of extra pieces. But you know, they're essentially
will be a numerical entry for every single frame indicating.
It's X Y and Z position X Y and Z rotation. That's
all the data that's being recorded via
UXF the scene replication,
which I'm going to talk about. I believe actually in the following slide.
Is going to kind of cover the rest, right? So we
have our trackers we have them assigned the game objects. Now we want
to be able to generate a playback scene right now. Essentially.
What I've created is a component that I
won't go too much in the technical details, but
effectively the way that it works is that it will scan
your scene for all game objects determine what's
being tracked and what has meaningful visual stimulus
not everything that is tracked has meaningful visual
stimulus. We actually if we go back to this video, for example,
we consider the floor you can kind of see in the background to be
meaningful visual stimulus. It doesn't move.
And so we want the ability to generate a scene and
taken all that data. And so
sort of that interface at the very top here sort of defines. Okay,
like these are the meaningful components within Unity that
that all like meaningful visual
stimulus will have let's generate a playback scene and
it'll just create that copy for you based off
of the current experiment the current environment States within your
editor.
So I hope that the answer your question anything. I want to want me
to elaborate on relative to that.
It is not guaranteed that the Privacy that
is created is full complete.
Because you mentioned that it determines by
itself which which opt-game objects
are meaningful and which are not so you've never
the object might seem not meaningful by
the by the script it might be meaningful to
the subject. So what actually does is that you can
you can change this less. However, you want you can add or remove meaningful
components. So if you were simulation happens to
have components that are not meaningful to other simulations or
our meaningful in your specific case, then
the script will know to replicate those and
it'll create an exact replica of
the hierarchy of your project with all those objects in there sort
of default States if they update over time at
all. Well, that's a tracker's job. And so when you create a
reflection any changes that happen to the object pass its initial
state will be recorded and reflected in the reflection.
Yeah, it is a sort of like a backup
in a way and you define exactly what
counts as a backup. So it is possible. Yes to come to create like
incomplete playback environments. If you don't Define it correctly.
However, the vast majority of cases are going to
have a very small set of actual meaningful visual components.
For example
Within within this scene, right if like anything,
let's look at the stimulus here this game object.
But because you can see it is guaranteed to
have a mesh filter component anything that you see will have that
component. And so if you want your playback scene to replicate anything
that you can see well
you include that component within the
within the scene generator
and so, you know, it can cover
all gaps. You just need to be able to account for any potential
gaps, but I would imagine
that the majority of use cases wouldn't go
too far outside of you know,
seven or eight components in total that create
meaningful visual stimulus.
Because just that mesh filter encompasses about 99% of
cases.
So what's the results it's actually
show you the playback system in action here.
So you can load in your data from a given directory. And this
is a very simple version of the interface. This is
sort of like the portable version and you
can kind of see it playing back here like a video player where you
know, you can pause play kind
of scrub through it and all those same movements you
saw in the earlier video are replicated here. All it's
doing is Reading in the data from your trackers. You can't
even tell that this scene is that carbon copy
of the scene? You saw earlier look exactly the same.
And so that's at its core.
How you get that set up up and running there's plenty
of other bits of information that will be contained, you know
within this within this interface as a
develops further, but you're going to see probably a
more complex version as we go into sort of the prototype for
the playback Suites.
moving into the case studies
and that's what I want to do next. I want
to move into the case studies and talk a little bit about those sort of
how the playback speed has been applied it
also how it originated.
So this may seem familiar to
a number of you here might be tired of
seeing it, but I'm sure it anyway.
So this environment so I'm not
going to go too much into the experiment itself just about the environmental features. We have
participants doing drone flight
through a dense Force environments flying laps around this
course, we have Gates we have trees. We have a path we have
gaze data in the background being constantly recorded by pupil labs.
And like that's what
we got going on in the environment right even just
by that basic description. There are huge
number of obstacles to doing like interesting
visual analysis on this scene. So for starters,
the rendering cost is enormous. If you're working in
VR you need to at least be hitting 90 frames per second consistently that's
really hard to do when you're also running an eye
tracker in the background have a realistic environment with realistic lighting.
And you know things of that nature.
So that's already a huge kind of burden on
your performance. So if you're interested in like creating
recordings of different camera perspectives of that scene.
Good luck. It's really really difficult to get up
and running. I would say it's pretty much impossible. Unless you have a separate
machine capable of like doing some
kind of remote connection.
But it's it's pretty much infeasible task beyond the
point because if you want to have another camera perspective you basically need
to double the entire day of your rendering cost this environment. It's all
rendering cost.
It's also really noisy, right? There's a ton
of clutter going on here a lot of bits and pieces of sort
of somewhat meaningful information here
and there they can kind of complicate The Gaze data and make it difficult
to interpret. So if you want to have 3D visualization within this
scene the playback system sort of emerged as
a natural extension of that desire. And so
that's what we sort of created in our prototype. So this
year is the sort of original version
of the playback system that was created specifically for this
experiment highlights a couple of things as a ton of information going
on here. So I want to be able to unpack a little bit of all
of this and describe it and brief. So we
have toward like the top left hand corner top right hand
corner. We have the actual. So this
is all recorded in one day to file so all the data for
the Drone itself and the Gaze was
sort of is kind of visualized in the corners at
the top. Don't pay that too much mind. We have buttons on
the left hand side that allow you to
On and off different visualizations and on
the bottom. You see the familiar playback interface
with a few more features a more robust speed slider
the ability to skip through frames via certain
like number of frames at a time and other little
feature that I'll talk about later right that in
that section at the bottom right that says image rendering. We'll come back
to that.
Go ahead.
So the
meaningful stimuli is essentially the entirety of
this environment.
To to some extent or another right whether it's the
trees and the distinction perhaps
between Trees close to the path trees Far From the Path the ground
itself the path itself the gates the
sky out in the distance. There's a
lot of potentially meaningful information and I
say potentially meaningful because in environment like this a
lot of your research is going to be exploratory. You don't know necessarily what
you're looking for. And so all pieces of environmental data
have the potential to be relevant in some sense or another.
So yeah, we're gonna start playing this video through and
this is kind of run you through this is
just me kind of going through some of the the basic features. I'm playing
with the speed slider here. So we're running it maybe like half speed
right now. We're now we're gonna go like frame by frame for a
little bits.
And so on we have again like more speed adjustments
on this sample flights and we
also have you can kind of see two different crosshairs.
This this is a story behind this right? So this
is a very simple as a problem. You were sort of talking about a very
simple overlay of your gaze within the the
2D screen or onto the 2D screen,
right? And we actually have two different crosshairs here because the problem
that we ran into sort of during data collection
on this experiment so
Initially the way we were recording gaze data was
by using the pupil Labs Unity API
to Output all the information to a
file. Right and we use that and accepted
that sort of as truth. What we didn't know is that
there were some issues the eye tracker that we were using with
pupilabs also recorded some additional post-processing which means
after we collected the data within Unity. We then need to
take it to another piece of software. We had to
essentially like remap a
lot of the a lot of the gays data and we wound up
getting completely different numbers after that. Those numbers were much more
accurate to what was actually happening, but they had
nothing to do with the data. We actually collected in unity
plus they were an entirely different formats and just
could not be visualized the same way and we
didn't know that was happening until we started visualizing the gays
Crosshair not just in 3D space, but also we're
not just in 2D space here, but in 3D space, oops actually
just skipped the entire video.
Let's pull that back. So we started to analyzing the scene
in 3D space. And with this
third person perspective. What we couldn't see in the two-dimensional view is
that we had times when the that red
beam which represents the incorrect one. The original
data be collected would end up going behind your drone, which is
you all have eyes that's impossible. It
does not happen. So
Clearly something was very visually wrong and we
didn't know that just looking at the numbers now, we could have visualized that in a number
of ways but having this already available made an incredibly easy
to decipher that problem. And so
we needed to do more computation right in
our original recording we had information about like where
your gaze was Landing what object it was hitting where on
that object. It was hitting we didn't have that anymore. We had
to do post processing the green beans now mapped
to somewhere entirely different than the red beam, but we were
able to import that data back into the playback system and I
made that mistake again. It just skipped it over. So we're
able to reimport that data back into the playback system and
Export additional information basically,
right a new mapping of what
your gaze is landing on at any given point in time and that
became really useful to us. It also
allowed us to do computation on values that
we never even collected initially. So I remember
at some point or another we decided that we
Is also computes participant heading and run
that through.
Now this is really easy in the playback system because we already had
something capable of exporting additional data
from our scene. So all we need to do is is use
the change in position over time across
frames and compute a new
file.
Right with the old file that also included our heading.
So all kinds of information can sort
of be extrapolated in ways that are sort of cohesive and
convenience through this playback system. Now those
those ideas aren't unique to the
playback Suite but they are
made I think a lot easier and again a lot more unified. Oh,
but there's one more thing that I did not mention.
About this system that I want to talk about. I'm gonna go back to this video for
the umpteenth time and talk about the bottom right hand corner, so
In the bottom right hand corner, we have something called image rendering. Now
what you can do with the playback Suites is once
you've put your data back into
unity and play it back frame by frame. You also have the ability to
render out every single one of those frames individual images and
in those images you can you can
demonstrate and I'll actually show here not only
can you demonstrate difference filters on
top of the camera. They may be visualized certain important piece
of information. And this one we have an example of sort
of distinct coloring of meaningful game objects
as they're close to the path and homogenous coloring
of game objects Far From the Path as shown
by all those solid color trees.
So that was a visualization. We were able to accomplish. We're also
able to get you know, those images output from
different camera angles as well. And if
you have a series of images, they can be compressed into a
single video and so as a result we then
have the power to record video from infinite camera perspectives
with any configuration of our different visualizations
within the scene.
And that's where I think the playback system gets really really interesting.
So yeah, that that is a at its
core sort of what this is all about.
Now the next case study.
Is going to be a lot more limited in its scope because this is
meant to be sort of integration test with the
portable version that I sort of demonstrated earlier and a novel
simulator. It looks like actually Google Slides still hasn't formatted
the video which is curious. Let's see if it wants to open it and
drive. I might be able to demonstrate this video is still processing. All
right, I'll talk about that while this downloads. Maybe we'll get somewhere with that.
So
Um, yeah, so essentially what
to sort of stress test the compatibility of this with a simulation that's
never seen before and the simulation that has paradigms that
are not present and I think a lot
of other pieces of software as well as not present
in anything. We've tested thus far right and so essentially we're
working with and maybe you'll see in a few seconds is a
car simulator derived from
Gabriel Diaz at RIT.
Which features a couple of things like randomly generated Road paths
Dynamic mesh construction and destruction on
objects that are actually important to the data
recording which is interesting as well as eye tracking on
top of that it will as a progresses
because the simulation is still in development will have
more realistic environments that will
produce some interesting noise and the potential for very interesting
visualizations. This video here
kind of demonstrates a little bit. We're not going to go too deep into all this.
Sure take my recommended settings go right ahead.
There we go. Sorry the video is a
little bit off kilter. I messed up an OBS and realized.
The drag this file but you know the actual simulation
here as it stands with the video I have right I was
very simple. It's just a car driving down a road, but there are a
lot of features you can't see so the road mesh can constantly
generating, you know,
the way that it's getting destroyed as you progress past it there are
multiple to different trials. So as you progressing at randomly generated, so
this is sort of the environment we want
to go into next and this
video is just sort of to demonstrate. You know, what we're looking at what we
plan on doing.
um, let's get back into
yes.
So yeah.
To recap I want to overview what the playback Suite
is best suited for it's really great. I believe for
research that's done with you
know, continuous data collection, whether that's continuous as
a result of I data whether that's a constantly moving person like
a character within your environment whether that's constantly moving
stimuli that you're interested in studying, you know,
all of that can then be played back frame by frame within the playback Suites
if you have high rendering costs. Well, like
I mentioned earlier that ability to offer multiple different camera perspectives without
the need to record anything additional at runtime
outside of your basic data becomes really useful because
you don't have to worry about you don't have to worry nearly
as much about your frame budget in order to make those extra visualizations
happen and in general
just any kind of complex three-dimensional or
interactive environment is going to have I think a lot of a
lot of data that could be interestingly played back using this system.
So what are we going next? We want to
sort of complete a test integration within that
that second case study that car
experiment. We want to get this software ready for
a major release so it can be used more broadly. I need
to spend plenty of time writing down guides and documentation on
how to use this because I'm sure as you've sort of understood up to
this point, there's a lot going on and there's more going on
than I've even talked about in order to make all
of this fall into place. So in order to do that, we need
to be very straightforward and very comprehensible.
And of course distribute the code and try to support
it for as long as possible.
But with all that said I
am now finished. So, thank you.
I don't know exactly to be honest, of course the
the amount of data you're going to get depends on your recording rate. So for
example, if you want to record every single frame, you're gonna get a ton of data
that might add up if your trials are particularly long, but that's
going to happen. Anyway, that's sort of an inevitability. If you're
using like a more consistent like 60 frame per second locked update,
then you won't be getting as much data now the actual
like I guess file size overhead introduced by
the playback Suite it's actually relatively minimal.
This is because it's reusing all the same assets that
already exist within your Unity project. And in a Unity project. The biggest
files are the 3D assets the actual
like list of Game objects all the components and
everything that follows is really small in comparison. Now,
of course, it will be a lot of overhead to perhaps have
to go over to make sure that everything's working correctly. But
you know fundamentally, it doesn't add too
too much I believe.
was not being overhead but rather than decide just
yeah.
To be honest, I have no idea. I don't think it megabytes
fermented. I'm sorry.
Go ahead.
her to
try to time like because you don't know in advance,
which trials you want to sort of.
organization so you
Right, you need a separate computer. It's
it's saying and then the file size is just
yeah.
So I think it's a reduction relative to
that. Oh, yeah.
No, I should add that. Like we don't we try to
avoid recording data that you're not going to record anyway, so any
data that's being recorded and
I guess excess of what any researcher already plans to
record is relatively minimal. It'll be a new column representing timestamp or
some other piece of information just necessary to
get the playback Suite working. We're actually trying to want to minimize the amount of
like frame by frame data collected but the
actual increase in the overall
output is minimal. I should also doubly mention that
you can use a single like replicated playback scene
for many different trials many different
trials so long as the recorded in that same environment.
the you first
you recording the actual
position Northern angles frame by frame by frame. Where do
you have some mechanism or reporting endpoint to particular parameterized motion
to kind of to reduce the file size
of
Beds. Yeah, so we're going for playbacks. They're entirely deterministic. And
so we are recording. We are expecting frame by
frame recordings. And that's how the unity experiment framework also works in
its expectation. So we're in line with that.
The graphics research whether they have a lot of stuff on this. I'm kind
of modeling modeling kind
of 0.5 Point motion where you know, this
Frame is here. Next frame is here next year modeling that
as like a close approximation of a function that represents
that motion and that functionally a lot less space than
the individual.
my friend
by Frank Northern
so curious for you the Messier that as a way to reduce your
file size.
Overall, no because frankly we're not that concerned with
the file size produced by the raw data recording in comparison.
For example, the image rendering that
happens afterward, which actually does have massive amounts of file size and
does need to be configured to you know, potentially reduce those those file
size of desired but the actual overhead because
it would take a very take a long time for your data design
accumulate to you know, megabytes behind
megabytes. It's just not a priority.
impression was
Performance via, so you're
obviously on your your offloading the multiple render
costs. So later on when you have to rent render it render
the other camera angle effect.
My question is what's the runtime overhead
of doing the I/O like are you are you
recording all these data to like any memory buffer
and running that at the simulation are you writing into the file as
you go what the size your buffers because that can have a big impact.
IO in general especially higher discs relative
to competitions in memory.
Yes, as you
go and keeping me the in-memory buffer higher
handling performs at runtime in terms of all
your IO out of this. Yes, that's a beautiful thing
about UXF. It handles all of that for me. I don't even
have to think about it but to answer your question so you XF and
the way that it records data, it does utilize that memory buffer approach. So
I believe at the end of either at
the end of Trials or end of blocks. I don't remember which offhand it
will then kind of begin a
multi-threaded process to be in like writing all of your content to
desk and so it's it's really really
good at handling that if you want to read more about UXF
I'm sorry. Say that again.
Yes, yes because UXF is excellent. They're
great.
Exactly. I think Jeremy you got a question.
Okay, beautiful. Okay an old one for Sasha?
So in terms of alternatives for economic recording
and what couple of people have been
doing it, they just were recording the player input and
they just enabled them to reconstruct the
scene afterwards, which would be even more spot to go. All she
need is the joystick accordingly if you have some, you
know, random variable generation that
you could also use random sees to fix them for each of
the trials. So have you explore this
option because even more yeah, I
definitely agree there. So that's one thing that I have considered. We
ultimately ruled it out for the sake of Simplicity and scope.
It's much easier to work with sort
of explicitly defined bits of data from my perspective, but
it is something I think that could be utilized effectively
in the future and
I would even add that. There's nothing within the existing architecture that
would prevent you from doing that. You would
still be able to with the well-defined tracker and reflection do
that input logging and input/output. You
just simply need to not write
like most the most of the examples. I showed you were trackers that
explicitly say it's going to be at this position at this time
and this rotation at this time, but you
don't have to record that you could just choose not to and it
said you could record the inputs and then in your reflection say when I when I
see these inputs execute these actions and so
that is another approach you can take just not one that I really
demonstrate or plan to investigate, you know within the semester I
have left, but thank you.
Of them. Well, what about the more complex affect animations?
Right? Because we said it's rotation and
position. So what if you have like animation transition which
here is not but if you have a
screen like some explosion happening the car accident or whatnot, right
or
A waterfall or a bird flying this flapping her
wings, that would not capture right now.
Yeah animation. So they're actually there are two
very interesting exceptions animation is one of them. So it's a
very good job. You can assess that out. The other one is Sound audio is
kind of an entirely different beast. And I
do want this software to eventually be compatible with both of those
those features because they can be really important. But the
way that you have to play them back is just fundamentally very different
so sound for example is something that only occurs
like only, you know begins at one point
in time. So if you scrub backwards in time, like when
do you know to
How was the sound going to play back? That's that's
a really complicated problem the isolate to think about a lot more and
then you know the follow-up to follow
that up with animation, which is a little bit easier right animation. Luckily is
is well, there are
many different ways to do animation, but you know luckily animation fundamentally
is just numerical states which
can still be played back. There's just
no native support for that. And so that problem will likely
be a little bit simpler to solve once I get around to you know, think about
that more in depth
Jerry
yeah.
So as with everything involved
me video games adding multiplayer.
Who gets complicated but the
nice thing is there is some degree
of like sort of innate
potential to handle that. So for
example, if you have different trackers recording different canvas
perspectives for all of you are multiplayer agents. Let's say
they're all playing on the same machine for simplicity's sake which they've likely
aren't honestly but let's say they're all playing on the same
machine. If you have those different camera perspectives, then you
can simply use the existing feature to swap between those perspectives
and apply visualization to them accordingly. If they're
playing across different machines. You got to
get creative. We still have the ability to import additional information.
So what you would likely
be doing is sort of the default information would be set to whatever
the default player is. So that perspective that
you're seeing of the Drone flying around if there are multiple drones. Let's say
then by default you would get the player one drone and you
have to be able to import you have to write your own sort
of custom import for additional multiplayer information.
Um, but yeah, it is multiplayers one of those things
where especially I know with with your lab
Dr. Gray, you know.
Very interesting and really kind of explodes the potential
complexity of this kind of software, but I
wanted to still be somewhat compatible at least.
So this project is so cool, like
being in the lab and like seeing you
guys you and Nate bill this it's a
tremendous and highly technically
challenging fee.
And so I guess I am more abstract question about are there
any particular hard lessons that you
've taken upon yourself as as
you've gone through this project.
Hmm. I have spent unreasonable amounts
of time agonizing over small bits
of code design and usability.
You know, I think I think that's probably the biggest Revelation that's come
is like out of this entire process is sort
of how to create a game systems
that are that are flexible that
make intuitive sense to users and that
will manifest themselves into actually like well-functioning
interfaces. You know, I've just on
the project you mentioned on this project. We've been sort of
reaping the consequences even just last night of small poor
decisions. I made in my design that you
know have like hours of consequence and time
waste and that's really really important for this kind of software. Right if one
feature is even a little bit poorly designed that creates
create hours of confusion waste tons of money tons
of time and so it's like super super important that
everything be like as easy and straightforward
as possible when things don't work. I want
the software to tell you why it doesn't work. You know, that's that's
another thing that I've been like trying to drill in.
So, yeah.
Oh.
You haven't gone yet.
Programming Paradigm.
I've had questions for my friends about this
in the past like what skills a paradigm.
Doesn't become useful and this
seems like a context where that's something you might considered.
Yeah, definitely. There are a lot of within the code structure.
A lot of the code is structured around sort of
a hierarchy of whether it's either hierarchies of
inheritance or hierarchies of sort of
Information management and so I try to isolate
as much as possible each subsystem and
its managerial tasks. I try
to leverage as intuitive as of inherent
inheritance structure as possible. Those are
sort of the two things that I'm like really thinking about the most because when
you write your custom code, I want you to be able to inherit what
already exists almost exactly copy and paste
the samples and just write the part
that you care about like, I want to see I want to see the
color change make the color change bam. It happens. Like that's what
I'm trying to go for here. So
so let's stop there. If you have additional
questions, please stick around and I'm sure savior will
be
Yes, thank you. Thank you.